William Temple Franklin Papers 1775-1819 Mss.B.F86
American Philosophical Society
William Temple Franklin Papers
1775-1819
Mss.B.F86
American Philosophical Society
4.75 Linear feet
The son of William Franklin, Royal Governor of New Jersey, William Temple Franklin worked as aide to his grandfather, Benjamin Franklin, when the latter served as minister to France during the American Revolution. A bonvivant, Temple received his highest public appointment as Secretary to the American delegation at the Treaty of Versailles in 1782-1783, largely through the influence of his famous grandfather, but never again attained a significant post. As Franklin's literary heir, he edited and published a three volume set of his grandfather's writings in 1817. He married his long time mistress a few months before his death in Paris in 1823. The William Temple Franklin Papers provides a richly detailed portrait of the life of the grandson of Benjamin Franklin, and consists largely of letters received during the years that Temple served as his grandfather's aide in France, 1776-1785. Although much of the correspondence is routine, during this period, Temple received regular reports from friends and diplomatic colleagues relaying information on the American Revolution, the course of diplomatic and peace negotiations, and French public opinion on Benjamin Franklin and the new United States. The collection is also a rich resource for information on the personal lives of the Franklins, including interesting correspondence from Temple's relatives William Franklin, Elizabeth Franklin, Sarah Franklin Bache, and Jonathan Williams, and his mistress Blanchette Caillot.
4.75 linear feet
Franklin, William Temple, 1760-1823
Biographical/Historical note
Shortly after his birth in London in 1760, William Temple Franklin was sent out to be raised by a string of foster mothers. The illegitimate son of Benjamin Franklin's illegitimate son William and of an unidentified woman of apparently ill repute, Temple was kept far away from the public eye as his father advanced in career and social standing. When Temple was two, his father married respectably and left England to become Royal Governor of New Jersey, and only at age four would Temple begin his slow integration into the fractious Franklin family.
Kept ignorant of his parentage, Temple was introduced into Franklin's Craven Street home as "William Temple," a protégé of his grandfather, while the expenses of his lodging and schooling were funneled quietly through Margaret Stevenson to his absent father. Temple enjoyed the benefits of an excellent education and an amiable social circle and was considered a charming, if sometimes irresponsible young boy, yet it was only years later, when he was asked to accompany his grandfather on his return to Philadelphia in the spring of 1775, that he was at last apprised of his identity. The news, as he soon discovered, was a mixed blessing. Simmering tensions between Benjamin and William over both personal and political differences came to head in May 1775 when the three generations of Franklins met in at Joseph Galloway's farm at Trevose, Bucks County, Pa., to reacquaint themselves and attempt to reconcile. Rather than reunion, however, this meeting provoked a rancorous split between the elder, headstrong Franklins, with the flighty Temple caught in the middle. Although Temple left Trevose with William to become acquainted over the summer, Benjamin insisted that he return to Philadelphia in the fall to begin college -- and not coincidentally, to remain under Benjamin's close supervision.
At the end of an indifferent year at the College of Philadelphia, Temple received news that his father had been declared "an enemy to the liberties of this country" and thrown into prison. Benjamin grew alarmed when Temple decided to travel to New Jersey late in the summer to console his step-mother Elizabeth, and wrote to his grandson to express concern for his safety being so near British lines, but beneath that, he feared that Temple was falling under the sway of Loyalist sympathies. Having already lost a son to the Tories, Benjamin was determined not to lose his grandson. In early September, Benjamin quashed Temple's request to visit his father in prison, claiming at first that useful intelligence might be passed to the enemy, but adding later that he prevented the visit out of "tender Concern" for Temple's welfare during the perilous trip to Connecticut.
In the long run, Benjamin won out in the contest for Temple's loyalties, and when the aging diplomat was called upon to travel to France to secure support for the American cause late in September 1776, Temple came along as his personal aide. From his grandfather's side, Temple was provided with a uniquely privileged view on the sensitive negotiations between the fledgling United States and the French crown, and his grandfather regularly favored him with highly visible assignments to prepare him for future betterment. In December 1777, for example, Temple was selected to deliver the critically important Treaty of Amity between France and the new United States to the French ministry.
Yet despite his grandfather's assistance, Temple did little to distinguish himself, attracting a chorus of doubters as time progressed. Grown into a feckless, seemingly aimless young man, Temple was inclined to dandyism and took to the social life in France with as deep an enthusiasm as his grandfather, but without the wit or intellectual depth, and certainly without the personal discipline and commitment to Republican principles. Worse, Temple seems to have acquired an aptitude for infelicitous choices, gladly embracing the Mesmerist fad, for example, despite his grandfather's reservations on the subject, and even joining the pro-Mesmer Société d'Harmonie. Perhaps to prove his mettle and his commitment to serious matters, Temple teamed up with the Marquis de Lafayette in the summer of 1779 (a fellow fan of Mesmer) to plan an invasion of Britain, but like many of Temple's plans, this one never came to pass.
Despite his grandson's insouciance, Benjamin continued to work on Temple's behalf, initiating him into his Masonic Loge des Neuf Soeurs and scheming, as he once had for William, to see Temple marry well. In 1781, Benjamin attempted to strike a match between Temple and Cunegonde, daughter of Franklin's beloved Mme Brillon. "Having almost lost my own daughter because of the wide distance between us," he wrote to Mme Brillon, "I hoped to find another one in you, and still another in your daughter, to take care of my old age." Citing Temple's Protestantism as an excuse, however, the Brillons rejected the union. In characteristic Franklin fashion, Temple rebounded by taking up with a married neighbor at Passy, Blanchette Caillot, with whom he had a natural son, Théodore.
Through his grandfather's influence in 1782 -- and over the opposition even of many of Benjamin's allies -- Temple landed the most important assignment of his career when he was appointed as Secretary to the Peace Commission. But rather than advancing his prospects, this appointment may actually have hindered them by piquing the jealousy and animosity of his rivals. It is likely that the failure of Benjamin's efforts to win a ministerial appointment for Temple in 1783 can be attributed to a combination of resentment over Benjamin's manipulation and Temple's personality, which everyone but Benjamin now considered disreputable. When Polly Stevenson visited Benjamin at Passy in 1784, even she was disimpressed with the man Temple had become, writing that he had become "so engaged in the pursuit of pleasure that he is not an amiable or respectable character."
Before their returning to the United States in 1785, Benjamin and Temple parlayed with William yet again in a half-hearted attempt to work out their differences. Although there was no reconciliation, William agreed (not entirely willingly) to aid his son by selling him his New Jersey and New York properties at a bargain price. When Benjamin died on April 17, 1790, Temple inherited his library and became his literary executor. Although this seemed to instill an enthusiasm in Temple over plans to publish his grandfather's works, once again things did not go as planned. Gathering the manuscript of the autobiography and some important correspondence that he intended to use to update it, Temple returned to England in 1792 only to find that a French translation of it had already appeared. He decided, however, to continue on with his project, working slowly to produce a more complete edition.
Reuniting with his father in 1792, still unmarried, Temple chafed under William's demands that he find a wife, and shortly after fathering another illegitimate child, Ellen, with the daughter of his father's second wife, Temple broke bitterly away and moved to Paris. Without his grandfather's guiding hand, Temple continued on the same aimless path. His three volume edition of the Memoirs of the Life and Writings of Benjamin Franklin did not appear until 1817. He lived the last six years of his life with his English mistress Hannah Collyer, whom he finally married a months before his death in 1823.
Scope and Contents note
The William Temple Franklin Papers provides a richly detailed portrait of the life of the grandson of Benjamin Franklin, concentrated in letters received by Temple in the years that he served as his grandfather's aide in France, 1776-1785. Although much of the correspondence is perfunctory, during this period, Temple received regular reports from friends and diplomatic colleagues relaying information on the American Revolution, the course of diplomatic and peace negotiations, and French public opinion on Benjamin Franklin and the new United States.
The collection is equally valuable for providing insight into the personal lives of the Franklins, their sometimes contentious family life, indiscretions, and their intricate web of personal quarrels and alliances. The letters from Temple's father William and step-mother Elizabeth provide a glimpse into the stress Temple must have endured during his father's imprisonment during the summer of 1776, and Temple was in regular friendly contact with his aunt Sarah Bache Franklin and kinsman Jonathan Williams. There are also over 40 letters from Blanchette Caillot, Temple's mistress and mother of his son who died early.
Upon calendaring, the W. T. Franklin Papers were bound into volumes in roughly chronological order. Although the collection has been rearranged chronologically, we have retained the original volume and folio numbers for reference purposes.
Related Archival Materials note
Several other collections at the APS relate to William Temple Franklin, including:
William Temple Franklin-George Fox Collection
William Temple Franklin-Charles Pemberton Fox Collection
Immediate Source of Acquisition note
Gift of Charles Pemberton Fox, 1840.
Bibliography
The Printed Materials Department also houses most of the works published or edited by William Temple Franklin, including:
Franklin, William Temple, The Private Correspondence of Benjamin Franklin (London, 1817). Call no.: B F85f763.
Franklin, William Temple, Memoirs of the Life and Writings of Benjamin Franklin, 3 vols. (London, 1818). Call no.: B F85f77.
See also:
Franklin, Benjamin, Mémoires de la Vie Privée ... Écrits par lui Même et Adressés à Son Fils (Paris, 1791). Call no.: B F85f76.
Franklin, William Temple, Sketch of William Temple Franklin's services to the United-States of America (Philadelphia, 1789). Call no.: Broadside 973 C583 no.482.
Other Finding Aids note
Most of the William Temple Franklin Papers are calendared in I. Minis Hays, Calendar of the Papers of Benjamin Franklin, Vol. 5 (Philadelphia: APS, 1908).
Naval History Note
The William Temple Franklin Papers contain several letters which may be of interest to naval historians:
Barry, John, 1745-1803.
Ross, John. Letter to William Temple Franklin. 1780 October 2. Owing to adverse winds they have not been able to sail. A brig has just arrived from Philadelphia reporting the safe arrival of the Alliance. Captain Pierre Landais was put under arrest and the Alliance was to be offered to Captain John Barry. 2 pages. (CII, 119).
Barclay, Thomas. Letter to William Temple Franklin. 1783 March 22. Relating to prize-money claimed by the Alliance and Commodore John Paul Jones' squadron. 1 page. (CV, 36).
Jones, John Paul, 1747-1792.
Jones, John Paul. Letter to William Temple Franklin. 1778 September 25. Tells of his letters to Dr. Franklin, Dr. [Edward] Bancroft, M. [Le Ray] de Chaumont, M. [Antoine Raymond Jean Gualbert Gabriel] de Sartine, etc., and his efforts to get a command. If disappointed again will be obliged to return to America unemployed, as he cannot remain inactive. 3 pages. (CI, 62).
Jones, John Paul. Letter to William Temple Franklin. 1778 October 13. Has written a letter to M. [Le Ray] de Chaumont which he requests William Temple Franklin to translate. Declares that his honor has received a public injury from M. [Antoine Raymond Jean Gualbert Gabriel] de S[artine] and that it must be righted. 1 page. (CI, 69).
Jones, John Paul. Letter to William Temple Franklin. 1778 October 28. Considers M. [Le Ray] de Chaumont's plan to buy a frigate or corvette to be commanded by him (Jones) would require too much time and negotiation. Has seen Mr. Joseph [P.] Whitall who is at Brest and who saw the Indian at Amsterdam, which could be armed and sail in two weeks. Declares M. [Antoine Raymond Jean Gualbert Gabriel] de Sartine has wronged him. Hopes he will be given command of the Indian and that M. de Sartine will give him credentials and testimonials to justify him before Congress and his friends. Has many enemies, as no man in the Navy has pursued the same line of service as himself. 3 pages. (CI, 71).
Jones, John Paul. Letter to William Temple Franklin. 1778 November 16. Requests him to explain a letter which he encloses. Has received another very kind from the Duke de la R[ochefoucauld]. Intends to leave for l'Orient shortly. 1 page. (CI, 77).
Jones, John Paul. Letter to William Temple Franklin. 1780 November 11. Anxiety about his Excellency's health; has not yet received any papers or power to administer the oath of allegiance; advises that the public dispatches be sent as soon as possible. 1 page. (CII, 130).
Jones, John Paul. Letter to William Temple Franklin. 1784 May 31. Thinks it would be more consistent for him not to appear at Court, when the Act of Congress is presented authorizing him to accept the Order of Military Merit. 1 page. (CVI, 32).
Truxton, Thomas, 1755-1822.
Franks, Major David Salisbury. Letter to William Temple Franklin. 1781 December 10. Fears that his prolonged stay, waiting for a vessel, will be very expensive to the Government at home. The number of people arrived with the Franch fleets of war have caused a scarcity of necessaries of life; prices are very high. The "St. James," Capt. [Thomas] Truxton, probably the first vessel which will sail for America about January 15. His situation very unpleasant and embarrassing. Was arrested the other day on suspicion of being a spy. 3 pages. (CIII, 149).
Franklin, William Temple. Letter to Thomas Jefferson. 1785 July 20. Arrangements made with Captain Thomas Truxton. 3 pages. (B F86.15).
Early American History Note
This is a large collection of William Temple Franklin papers, most of which were written while he was serving alongside his grandfather in France as the secretary of the American mission there. The bulk of the collection is correspondence written to William Temple Franklin during the American Revolution. Franklin had a wide network of friends and associates, and this correspondence captures the range of dealings Franklin had in France. As secretary, he received intelligence, requests, reports of military actions, especially those pertaining to naval actions in the Atlantic, and various other communications. As a private individual, Franklin had relations with many merchants, traders, and land speculators and continued to cultivate these relationships while in Europe. The Collection also includes a diary kept in an almanac for much of 1785, catalogued separately in MOLE.
Combined with Benjamin Franklin’s Papers, the account books from the delegation, the Benjamin Franklin Bache Collection, and the John Adams Papers on microfilm, the APS has an extraordinarily strong record of the United States’ diplomacy during the American Revolution. Notable among the correspondents to William Temple Franklin is John Paul Jones, who was a regular correspondent to both William Temple and Benjamin Franklin.
The early portion of the collection contains a series of letters between William and Eliza Franklin and William Temple Franklin written before the American Revolution. The long letters touch upon William Temple’s education and on politics. The personal nature of the letters also provides insight into the family relations of the Franklin family during this very divisive period of the family’s history. Numerous letters from Sarah Franklin Bache and Benjamin Franklin Bache to William Temple can also be found in this collection.
This collection, along with the various other Fox Collections, chronicles William Temple Franklin’s career after the American Revolution, much of which was spent in Europe. William Temple Franklin inherited his grandfather’s papers, which he edited for publication, and later bequeathed to George Fox, whose family gifted them and William Temple Franklin’s papers to the APS.
Adams, John, 1735-1826; Bache, Benjamin Franklin, 1769-1798; Bache, Richard, 1737-1811; Bache, Sarah Franklin, 1743-1808; Barclay, Thomas, 1728-1793; Caffiéri, Jean Jacques; Caillot, Blanchette; Carmichael, William, d. 1795; Chaumont, Jacques-Donatien Leray de, 1725-1803; Deane, Silas, 1737-1789; Feutry, Aimé Ambroise Joseph; Foulke, John, 1757-1796; Fox, George, 1759-1828; Fox, Joseph Mickle, 1757-1784; Franklin, Benjamin, 1706-1790; Franklin, William, 1731-1813; Grand, Ferdinand; Grand, Henri Maximilien, 1757-1827; Houdon, Jean Antoine, 1740-1828; Jay, John, 1745- 1829; Jefferson, Thomas, 1743-1826; Jeffries, John, 1745-1819; Jones, John Paul, 1747-1792; Kéralio, Agathon Guynement, chevalier de; La Rochefoucauld, Louis Alexandre, duc de; Lafayette, Marie Joseph Paul Yves, marquis de, 1757-1834; Laneuville, Louis Pierre Panot Lombart, chevalier de, 1744-ca.1800; Le Roy, Jean Baptiste; Le Veillard, Louis-Guillaume, -- 1733-1794.; Lloyd, Richard Bennett; Malesherbes, Chrétien Guillaume de Lamoignon de,1721-1794.; Mayo, Joseph, d.1785; Mesmer, Franz Anton, 1734-1815; Morrelet, Abbé André, 1727-1819; Paine, Thomas, 1737-1809; Pyne, William; Ross, John, 1729-1800; Schaffer, John; Trumbull, Jonathan, 1710-1785; Vaughan, Benjamin, 1751-1835; Vaughan, John, 1756-1841; Warren, Winslow; Williams, Jonathan.; American Revolution; Americans Abroad; Balloons--Early works to 1800; Business and Skilled Trades; Business Records and Accounts; Diplomatic History; Diplomatic Material; Family Correspondence; France--Foreign relations--United States; France--History--Louis XVI, 1774-1793; France--Social life and customs--18th century; General Correspondence; International Travel; Land and Speculation; Marriage and Family Life; Mesmerism; Military History; Philadelphia (Pa.)--Social life and customs--1783-1815; Philadelphia (Pa.)--Social life and customs--Revolution, 1775-1783; Political Correspondence; United States--Foreign relations--France; United States--History--1783-1815; United States--History--Revolution, 1775-1783; United States--History--Revolution, 1775-1783--Peace; United States--Politics and government--1783-1815
- William Temple Franklin Papers, 1775-1790; Mss.B.F86; 4.5 lin. feet
  - to William Temple Franklin, 1775 May 29; ALS, 2p.; Williams, Jonathan Jr.
    Scope and Contents note
    On his departure from London with Franklin for America. News of friends.
  - to William Temple Franklin, 1775 July 29; ALS, 2p.; Woolford, Mrs. D.
    Referring to the kind reception William Temple Franklin received from his father (Gov. William Franklin) on arriving in America.
  - to William Temple Franklin, 1775 July 31; ALS, 2p.; Elphinston, James
    Giving advice to William Temple Franklin; hopes he will return to England to complete his education.
  - to William Temple Franklin, 1775 Sept. 14; ALS, 2p.; Franklin, William
    Giving his son advice about his studies. Several references to his father, Benjamin Franklin.
  - to William Temple Franklin, 1775 Sept. 25; ALS, 2p.; Franklin, Elizabeth
    Sending items of news about friends and acquaintances. Tells of the Major's [?] marriage.
  - to William Temple Franklin, 1775 Oct. 9; ALS, 3p.; Franklin, William
    Inquiring about his son's studies, his health, etc. Advice about letter writing.
  - to William Temple Franklin, 1775 Oct. 26; ALS, 2p.; Franklin, William
    Refers to the dancing and fencing schools. Has a translation of Livy, but thinks his son should not use one.
  - to William Temple Franklin, 1775 Oct. 30; ALS, 1p.; Franklin, William
    Refers to a barrel of oysters Mrs. Franklin is sending to him. Wishes to know when his father is expected home.
  - to William Temple Franklin, 1775 Nov. 9; ALS, 2p.; Franklin, Elizabeth
    Refers to articles of dress purchased for her Mrs. [Richard] Bache. Items of local news about mutual friends and acquaintances.
  - to William Temple Franklin, 1776 Jan. 22; ALS, 2p.; Franklin, William
    Complains of the abuse he and his wife have been subjected to recently. Speaks of his difficult situation. The indignities he has received. Much concerned about his wife who has no relatives in this country; refers to slights she has received from his own relatives. Wants a copy of "Common Sense" [by Thomas Paine, Philadelphia, 1776].
  - to William Temple Franklin, 1776 Feb. 5; ALS, 2p.; Franklin, William
    Is surprised that all his friends did not hear of reports spread about him. Refers to money matters; tells his son to be economical, as he has little to give him. Wishes a copy of the 3d edition of "Common Sense."
  - to William Temple Franklin, 1776 March 14; ALS, 2p.; Franklin, William
    Is greatly concerned about his father's proposed journey to Canada. Thinks it ill-advised and dangerous. Requests his son to send him several political pamphelts. Advises him not to neglect his studies in Latin and French.
  - to William Temple Franklin, 1776 March 25; ALS, 1p.; Franklin, William
    Giving his son directions how to come to Amboy when he gets his holidays. Refers to money matters between him, his son and Mr. [Richard] Bache.
  - to William Temple Franklin, 1776 May 8; ALS, 3p.; Franklin, William
    Reproves his son for spending his allowance too fast. Asks for certain numbers of the "[Pennsylvania] Evening Post" and "Pennsylvania Ledger."
  - to William Temple Franklin, 1776 May 22; ALS, 1p.; Franklin, William
    Encloses a due note to be given to Mr. [Richard] Bache for collection from Mr. Hooper.
  - to William Temple Franklin, 1776 June 3; ALS, 1p.; Franklin, William
    Reproves his son for imprudent spending of his allowance. Is glad to hear of his father's safe return; would be glad to hear that he had resolved to quit all public business. Requests several copies of pamphlet "Strictures on Common Sense." [True Interest of America Impartially Stated, in certain Strictures, on a Pamphlet entitled Common Sense. By an American (Charles Inglis), Philadelphia, 1776.]
  - to William Temple Franklin, 1776 June 13; ALS, 1p.; Franklin, William
    Reproaches his son for not being more punctual in attending to his orders. Anxious to hear how his father is after his recent journey.
  - to William Temple Franklin, 1776 June 25; ALS, 1p.; Franklin, William